<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Friendly monitor laying open the crying sins of cursing, swearing, drinking, gaming, detraction, and luxury or immodesty ... : in five short discourses ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2225</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R777</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12181720</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12181720</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55678</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40498)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55678)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 890:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Friendly monitor laying open the crying sins of cursing, swearing, drinking, gaming, detraction, and luxury or immodesty ... : in five short discourses ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Sam. Crouch ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Vices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian ethics.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55678:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55678:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Friendly Monitor, Laying open THE CRYING SINS OF Curſing, Swearing, Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Gaming, Detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Luxury or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modeſty.</p>
            <p>Piouſly intended for Correcting the Errors of this Vicious Age; in which, under the Name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, Men live like Heathens.</p>
            <p>In Five Short Diſcourſes, in which is ſhewn the Unreaſonableneſs and great Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs of theſe Vices, and ſome Means propoſed for their Cure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Sam. Crouch,</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Popes-head-Alley,</hi> againſt the <hi>Royal-Exchange,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:55678:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55678:2"/>
            <head>THE Friendly Monitor, Laying open the CRYING SINS OF Curſing and Swearing, And propoſing ſome REMEDIES For their, CURE.</head>
            <div type="text">
               <p>
                  <hi>HEar, O Earth, the words of my mouth,</hi> Deut. 32. 'Tis you was Created by the Almighty, for the Son<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:55678:3"/> of Men to walk on; but, behold, they have ſet you over their heads, admir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Duſt and Clay, enamour'd with your Filth and Corruption, and willingly venturing their Souls for the purchaſe of your<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Droſs; but <hi>Heaven</hi> they have brought under their feet, and trample moſt prophanely on the moſt Holy <hi>Name</hi> of God, while they ſhew reſpect to you. For are they not come to that impiety, that having little regard to the Commandments, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are ſtrictly enjoyn'd <hi>not to Take his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> vain;</hi> and taught, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot to ſpeak of him, but with all the Reſpect and Reverence poſſible, they lay aſide all Religious Modeſty and Shame, and not only make his Name <hi>Common,</hi> but vilely proſtitute it to all their own vain, idle and wicked ends?</p>
               <p>For where can a man turn, but his Ears are ſoon ſtruck, too often on both ſides, with horrid Swearing, raſh Oaths, frightful Curſing and abominable Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies; enough to make a man think, he's encompaſs's rather with wicked Spirits and Fiends, than Men, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs themſelves Chriſtians? Is it not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55678:3"/> with theſe Prophanations they give a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh to their Sports and Entertainments? With theſe they ſet off their Jeſts and Narratives; theſe they mix with their Cups; with theſe they ſanctifie their Debauches: With theſe they add terror to their Paſſions, power to their Commands, authority to their Quarrels; and if the very Horſes and Dogs are not ready at the beck of their Humor, are not theſe made uſe of for <hi>Spurs</hi> and <hi>Whips?</hi> Heaven and Hell are immediately ſtirr'd up, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the <hi>Great Gulf</hi> that is betwixt them, they bring <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Devil</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one breath.</p>
               <p>This is an excellent Character now of a People, that pretends to <hi>believe</hi> in God and <hi>love</hi> him. He ſays expreſly, <hi>Thou ſhalt not prophane the Name of thy God,</hi> Deut. 19. 12. and they ſpare not his Name even in the worſt of propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; taking it often in their mouths, but to its diſhonor; and dragging it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Streets, to ſerve as the Mockery of their Paſſions, of their Exceſſes and Fury. Chriſt our Lord confirms this Command to all his Followers: <hi>But I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55678:4"/> ſay unto you, Swear not at all, neither by Heaven, nor by Earth;</hi> Matth. 5. 34. <hi>neither by any other Oath,</hi> as his Apoſtle adds, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. 12. And they, like per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe and rebellious Children, mix their Oaths with all their diſcourſes; ſwear by Heaven and Earth, and call in God, and all that is Sacred, to witneſs the Truth of their impertinent, idle, and often Lying Extravagancies.</p>
               <p>And is not this a miſery, that men ſhould thus forget their Duty, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict their Profeſſion and ſo grievouſly offend their God? their God, whom the Angels adore, before whoſe Throne all the Heavenly Spirits fall down and worſhip, giving glory, and honour, and praiſe, to his Holy Name for ever and ever: He it is, theſe Men ſtand before without Reverence or awe, and ſo little think of Praiſing, that they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually belching out againſt him In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries and Contempts, under all the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Oaths and Swearing, that their Paſſion and Folly can ſuggeſt to them. So that however the Holy Scripture re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends to us, that we be ever mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of our God, it were, in ſome man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55678:4"/> to be wiſh'd, that theſe Scandalous Sinners would rather forget him, ſince they remember him ſo often, for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end, than to Swear by him and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane his Name.</p>
               <p>And how wretched an abuſe is this of the Gifts of God! For why did he give man a Tongue and Speech, but to be the <hi>Voice</hi> of all other creatures, for himſelf and them to give Thanks and Praiſe, and in humble Prayers, to petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for relief in all his Neceſſities? And inſtead of this, theſe men have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graded themſelves beneath all other creatures, taking part with the very Devils, and, in their language, diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noring their God, and blaſpheming the hand that made them.</p>
               <p>Thus by their frequent Oaths and habitual Swearing they offend againſt the Lord of Heaven, and in proportion to the Crime committed againſt him, are likewiſe injurious to themſelves. For firſt, is it not moſt evident, that by this deteſtable Vice, they ſhut the hand of the divine Bounty, and deprive themſelves of that Fatherly Protection and thoſe Heavenly Graces, with which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55678:5"/> God is wont to aſſiſt and bleſs his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants? For how can they expect his Gifts, who thus, at every turn, are ſo affronting to the Giver? Have they not rather reaſon to fear, they are caſt off and forſaken by him, whom they have firſt thus wretchedly forſaken?</p>
               <p n="2">2. They make themſelves incapable of ſaying their Prayers. For, with what face can they appear before the Lord, and ask him Favors, whom in their ordinary diſcourſes they ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lify and contemn? How can they ſay <hi>Our Father,</hi> and ſalute him with that Title of love, whoſe Honor they tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under their feet, and to whom they ſhew no more reſpect, than is due to the worſt of enemies? And when they ſay, <hi>Hallow'd be thy Name,</hi> muſt not their Conſciences neceſſarily turn upon them? For how can they ſeriouſly pray, that his <hi>Name</hi> may be <hi>Hallow'd,</hi> that is, <hi>Bleſſ'd</hi> and <hi>Praiſ'd</hi> by all Creatures, who make it their common practice to diſhonor and prophane it? They, by their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Speeches, are making it contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible to the world, and then in their Prayers ſay <hi>Hallow'd be thy Name,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:55678:5"/> What greater Mockery can there be than this? Might not <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> with as good reaſon, in his impious Banquet, Dan. 5. 2. have <hi>Pray'd</hi> for the <hi>hallowing</hi> the Veſſels of the Temple, when he brought them forth amongſt his Wives and Concubines, and drank in them Praiſes to his Gods of Silver and Gods of Gold? Such a Prayer for <hi>Sanctifying</hi> thoſe Veſſels, whilſt he was in the very act of <hi>Prophaning</hi> them, would have been the only way to outdo the devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Swearing Chriſtians, who pray, if they pray at all, that the <hi>Name</hi> of God may be <hi>hallow'd,</hi> and with their next breath prophane it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt their Cups and Concubines; and if it be for their advantage to have it brought forth on the <hi>Counter,</hi> to gain credit to their falſe Proteſtations, ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple not by repeated Oaths, to ſacrifice it to their Intereſt, to their Gods of Silver and Gods of Gold. Thus <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzar</hi>-like, with their impious lips they pollute that which is moſt Holy, and have no other poſſible excuſe for being thus prophanely abſurd and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, but only the ill Cuſtom of a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55678:6"/> Raſh and Heedleſs Humor, by which as they <hi>Swear,</hi> ſo they <hi>Pray</hi> they <hi>Know not what.</hi> But that <hi>Hand,</hi> which writ the fate of that Unhappy Prince, writes, no queſtion, their Crimes and Deſtiny on every wall; and tho they, Blind and Obſtinate Sinners, obſerve it not; yet it will, one day, be produc'd againſt them; and then, when in the Severity of the Puniſhment, they too late begin to ſee the weight of their Sins, what will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, but repeated Cries of Deſpair, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Repentance? But Heaven will be then as Deaf to their Cries as they had been before to all its invitations to amendment.</p>
               <p>But let us ſuſpend their Sentence a little, while we view another part of their Crime, and that is the Sin of <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> which commonly hangs to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; for <hi>Swearing</hi> and <hi>Curſing</hi> for the moſt part go together; and have this only difference, that <hi>Swearers,</hi> by diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noring the Name of God, ſeem to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own and abandon him; but <hi>Curſers</hi> take a ſtep more back ſtill, and call on the Devil for help; ſo that, while, by the former Sin, they forſake God; by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55678:6"/> the other, they go to the Devil. And this is moſt abominable in all its bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. For 1. if we conſider thoſe, who on ſlight and trivial occaſions throw out <hi>Curſes</hi> againſt <hi>themſelves,</hi> at every turn calling for <hi>Plagues,</hi> the <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> on their own heads, what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Madneſs can there poſſibly be than this? To ſee men, who, beſides being bound by the Law of Nature and of God, to preſerve themſelves, are otherwiſe ſo tender and nice, even to a Vice, that they cannot bear the leaſt Inconvenience, the leaſt Pain, Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction or Diſappointment, but they preſently become uneaſy, impatient and paſſionate; to ſee theſe, I ſay, in their frequent Wiſhes, as it were, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunatly calling for the worſt of <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> on themſelves, wiſhing for <hi>Hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire</hi> and hourly <hi>Praying for</hi> what they moſt <hi>fear,</hi> and for the <hi>deſtruction</hi> of that, which their whole concern is to <hi>preſerve:</hi> What ſhall I fay of them? but that the <hi>Outrages</hi> of <hi>Bedlam</hi> are <hi>Reaſonable</hi> in compariſon of their <hi>Folly:</hi> And that if they would but lay down <hi>this Madneſs,</hi> and take up <hi>theirs,</hi> 'twould
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55678:7"/> be no ungrateful Exchange to ſuch of their True Friends, who would be more contented to ſee in them an <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> than a <hi>Wicked</hi> Frenzy. And how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they may, think it more <hi>Manly</hi> and <hi>Great</hi> to play with <hi>Hell-fire</hi> and <hi>Damnation,</hi> than with <hi>Straws, Paper</hi> or <hi>Ribbands;</hi> yet certainly theſe are the more harmleſs, and I think no leſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming; ſince all the <hi>Greatneſs,</hi> that is in the former, is only like the Swelling of <hi>Venemous Creatures,</hi> which grow <hi>big</hi> indeed, but with nothing but <hi>Poyſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. If we look on theſe Sinners in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their <hi>Neighbour,</hi> they are of all the moſt Uncharitable; tho this indeed be no more than a Conſequence of their former Crime: for they that are thus their own enemies, as to pray for the worſt of evils on themſelves, cannot be well expected to ſay better Prayers for their Neighbors. And therefore it is, on the leaſt Provocation, you may hear them wiſhing for all the <hi>Plagues, Devils</hi> and <hi>Damnation</hi> on every one that ſtands in their way, that thwarts their humor, or appears in the leaſt injurious to them. Theſe are their <hi>Seconds</hi> call'd in, on all
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55678:7"/> occaſions to revenge every affront offer'd to their Cravat-ſtring, Perriwig or Toes: ſo that a man muſt walk very cautiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to eſcape having the Devil let looſe at him ſome time in the day. For theſe men have him ſo ready in their mouths, that he ſeems to be kennel'd there, and the leaſt occaſion makes him fly out.</p>
               <p>And this is an excellent ſort of Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Spirit now, which is as exact in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Precepts of Chriſt, as the worſt of Heathens could deſire. He ſays, <hi>Love your Enemies,</hi> Math. 5. 44. and a little thing ſerves to make them <hi>Curſe their Friends.</hi> He ſays, <hi>Bleſs them that Curſe you,</hi> and their Bleſſing is of <hi>Plagues and Devils.</hi> He ſays, <hi>Do good to them that hate you;</hi> and their good is, to wiſh them <hi>confounded with Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Evils.</hi> He ſays, <hi>Pray for them which deſpitefully uſe you,</hi> and their Prayer is a Hearty <hi>Dam ye.</hi> Thus they defeat the moſt fundamental Maxims of Chriſtianity, and make the enemies of the Goſpel blaſpheme the Holy Name, which they profeſs.</p>
               <p>And is not this a moſt abominable and ſcandalous Practice, for men thus
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55678:8"/> to trample on that Law, which they pretend to follow, and, upon every provocation, to turn their anger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God? What mercy can they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from him, whom they thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily offend? And with what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion muſt they one day appear before him, whoſe Name they have ſo wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly prophan'd, whoſe Honor they have expos'd to Scorn and Contempt, whoſe Commandments they have broken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remorſe? Will not then all their vain and raſh <hi>Oaths,</hi> their deteſtable <hi>Curſes</hi> riſe up in Judgment againſt them, and that <hi>Damnation,</hi> they have ſo often wiſh'd to others, fall to their own ſhare?</p>
               <p>This, there's too much reaſon to fear, will be their unhappy lot, if they take not care to reform theſe Vices in time, and ſhake off theſe ill habits, before Death ſummons them to appear before their Lord. Will it not therefore be a labor well beſtow'd, if by ſincere en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours and a ſeaſonable Repentance they ſtrive to prevent this doom of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery? For my part, the Zeal I have for God's Honor, and the Compaſſion due to my Neighbors and Brethren in their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55678:8"/> Souls diſtrefs, make me heartily deſire they would turn their thoughts and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours this way. I wiſh 'twere in my power to contribute to this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good: I dare not preſume to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect; however, if I lay before them ſome Means, or Helps, I hope Chriſtian Charity will be ſufficient to excuſe me.</p>
               <p>I am very ſenſible, how difficult it is to overcome an <hi>ill Habit;</hi> and yet I am perſuaded, there's no body, that ſets himſelf ſeriouſly about this work, with the application due to ſo great an affair, but, by the Bleſſing of Heaven, will ſoon gain ground, and by degrees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come entire Maſter of himſelf: But then,</p>
               <p n="1">1. He muſt not fail, in frequent and fervent Prayers, daily to beg the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Divine Grace, which is the only Remedy of all our evils, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which all our endeavours will moſt certainly be fruitleſs. He muſt often, with <hi>David,</hi> cry out, <hi>Make haſt, O God, to deliver me, make hast to help me, O Lord;</hi> Pſ. 70. and as often beg, that the <hi>Seraphim,</hi> that touch'd the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean lips of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Iſa. 6. 6. will with
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55678:9"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:55678:9"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:55678:10"/> a Coal from the ſame Altar of God, touch his lips and mouth and purge them from all iniquity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As for Perſons of Quality, who know what <hi>Honor</hi> is, and are very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of every thing that touches them in that point, ought not they to conſider how unbecoming and unworthy it is in them, frequently to diſhonour him, from whom <hi>all Honor</hi> proceeds, and in their daily diſcourſes to caſt out ſo many indignities againſt the divine Majeſty, which, if offer'd to their own Perſons, they could not bear without rage? And as for others of a lower rank, 'tis not leſs unreaſonable in them, ſince for Worms of the earth to be ſo often flying at the Infinit Majeſty of God, is moſt arrogant and Intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And may not a ſerious conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this be ſome check to this evil?</p>
               <p n="3">3. What if theſe Offenders would frame a lively Idea of thoſe eternal flames, which are prepar'd as the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of their crimes? and that this may make a due impreſſion on their minds, what if they imagine, that for every <hi>Raſh Oath</hi> or <hi>Curſe,</hi> that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55678:10"/> comes out of their mouths at preſent, they were to have a <hi>burning Coal</hi> laid on their <hi>Tongues,</hi> tho' for five minutes only; would not this, if 'twere to be really ſo, teach them to bridle their Tongues and ſoon fright away their ill Cuſtom? And why ſhould not the thoughts of Hell, with Rational men, work the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect? They are generally careful to avoid and prevent Miſchief; and why not that above all, which is Eternal?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Why ſhould not every man ſet up a <hi>Court of Juſtice</hi> within his own <hi>breaſt,</hi> and as the Common-wealth has appointed certain <hi>Penalties</hi> for <hi>Public Offenders,</hi> ſo every one aſſign certain <hi>Mulcts</hi> or <hi>Puniſhments</hi> for every Noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious or Scandalous Sin, which they commit? And what if one, that is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to <hi>Swearing</hi> &amp;c would, for every Sin of this kind, fine himſelf, according to his ability two-pence, a groat, ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, &amp;c. to be given to the Poor, or employ'd in any other Charitable uſe? Would not this, by degrees, make him more careful; and for the ſaving his Mony, oblige him to ſave his Soul?</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:55678:11"/>
               <p>Thus might every one, that is truly deſirous to reform any ill Cuſtom, find out Means to effect it. And 'tis but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary this in particular ſhould be ſeriouſly thought on, ſince, like a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious Diſtemper, it has over-run the greateſt part of man-kind: 'tis this which is moſt Public and Scandalous, and by offending all pious ears of Little and Great, muſt neceſſarily draw after it the Puniſhment of many Mill-ſtones, and make it to have been better that ſuch men had never been born, than thus under the Name of Chriſtians, to have taken part with and liv'd like Heathens</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <trailer>The next Sheet ſhall be <hi>Of the Sin of Drunkenneſs.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="colophon">
               <p>Printed for <hi>Sam. Crouch</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Popes-head-Alley,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal-Exchange,</hi> 1692.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:55678:11"/>
            <head>THE Friendly Monitor. OF THE SIN OF DRUNKENNESS.</head>
            <div type="text">
               <argument>
                  <p>Drunkards excluded the Company of God's People, and from the Number of the Bleſſed. Sober Drunkards not much leſs Criminal than Sottiſh ones: Their Sins lay'd open, and Pretexts for ſuch Drinking ſhew'd <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AN Antient Father ſays, <hi>Drunkenneſs</hi> is a <hi>Devil;</hi> how then can I. better go about to lay this Evil <hi>Baſil.</hi> Spirit, than with the <hi>Word of God</hi> in my
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55678:12"/> Hand? <hi>Awake</hi> therefore <hi>ye Drunkards, and weep and howl all ye Drinkers of Wine,</hi> Joel 1. 5. For, behold, the Lord of Hoſts has pronounc'd <hi>Wo's:</hi> againſt you, declar'd you miſerable and wretched both here, and hereafter. He has ſet a <hi>Mark</hi> on you like <hi>Cain,</hi> and commanded his People to run from you as from a Peſtilential Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper: <hi>Be not amongſt Wine-bibers,</hi> ſays he to them by <hi>Solomon;</hi> Prov. 23. 20. And by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> he enjoyns them, <hi>not to keep Company with any Man that is</hi> but <hi>call'd a Drunkard,</hi> 1 Cor. 5. 11. And he has expreſly cut you off from the Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of Eternal Life: <hi>Be not</hi> therefore <hi>deceived,</hi> ſays he, for neither <hi>Thieves, nor Covetous, nor Drunkards, ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 9, 10. Again he repeats this Decree, <hi>The works of the Fleſh are manifeſt, Envyings, Murders, Drunkenneſs, of the which I tell you, that they which do theſe things, ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> Gal. 5. 19, 21.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee your ſelves in plain terms rejected by the Almighty, and a Two-fold Sentence paſs'd againſt you: <hi>Firſt,</hi> whereby you are Condemn'd as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for the Company of his People. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> whereby you are for ever excluded
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55678:12"/> from the number of the Bleſſed. <hi>Awake ye Drunkards, and weep and Howl all ye Drinkers of Wine.</hi> We'll now enquire into the Reaſons of theſe Two Decrees, and, by this take a full view of the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Crime.</p>
               <p>And Firſt, why the Servants of God are forbid the Company of ſuch as are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to this Vice. We read in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> having a ſtrict charge given them not to mix with the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites,</hi> nor the <hi>Hittites,</hi> or other People of the Land, but to 'avoid all Society with them; and the reaſon was, that thus declining their Company, they might be out of danger of being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by them, and ſo continue Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to their God. The ſame without doubt is the reaſon why all good People are enjoyn'd not to company with Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, becauſe their Vice as it is moſt Scandalous in it ſelf, ſo it is deſtructive of all Goodneſs; it takes off all <hi>Modeſty</hi> and <hi>Shame,</hi> which are the common Bars Nature has ſet up againſt Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; it makes him that is Inſolent, Prouder; him that is Cruel, Fiercer; and irritates the Leacher, to the laying aſide all thoughts either in regard to Decency
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55678:13"/> or Scandal. 'Tis this which puts Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies into Diſorder, and draws on them Confuſion and Ruin; it drowns Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, overthrows Religion, and like a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge carries away before it all Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to Good. In fine, it extinguiſhes <hi>Reaſon</hi> in Man, and having taken away this his <hi>Guide,</hi> leaves him to the conduct of Blindneſs and Paſſion; ſo that as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he becomes altogether Senſeleſs, and like the Idols of the Gentiles, has Eyes and Sees not, Ears, and Hears not; at other times he puts on the Beaſt, and becomes more fierce and intractable than they; and if one ſhould ſay, that upon occaſion, a Man might with as much ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity meet the moſt furious Inhabitants of <hi>Africk,</hi> as with ſome ſort of theſe Amphlbious Domeſtick Animals; we have had too many ſad Inſtances to confirm the Truth of it. Hiſtory affords us one moſt remarkable in <hi>Alexander,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Two Friends, <hi>Clytus,</hi> and <hi>Lyſima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> the one he expos'd to a Lion, the other to his <hi>Drunken Self;</hi> and while he that was turn'd looſe to the Beaſt eſcap'd, the other fell a Sacrifice to the Fury of his Diſtemper'd Brain.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:55678:13"/>
               <p>And while we ſee <hi>this Vice</hi> thus an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Enemy to Vertue, and wholly incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the manifold Duties of a Chriſtian Life, we can have no reaſon to wonder why there is this ſtrict charge given to Chriſtians, of avoiding the Company of all ſuch as are unfortunate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly corrupted with it; for if there be juſt reaſon to run from a Contagion, for fear of its Infection, there is much more reaſon to fly ſuch Company, who are little better than ſo many Factors for Hell, who trade in Wickedneſs, and help to ruin Souls. For if the <hi>Word of God</hi> expreſly commands Chriſtians to live <hi>Soberly,</hi> ought not they to be avoided as Enemies to Chriſtianity, whoſe Life is little better than a repeated <hi>Intemperance,</hi> and whoſe Company is a moſt certain encouragement to <hi>Exceſs?</hi> If the Word of God enjoyns us to live <hi>Juſtly,</hi> that is, to diſcharge <hi>every Duty</hi> incumbent us, either in regard to <hi>Family,</hi> in ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; to <hi>Children,</hi> in ſeeing them duly Educated; to <hi>Creditors,</hi> in taking care that they be Satisfied; to the <hi>Poor,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving them with what we can Spare; to every <hi>Neighbour,</hi> in giving them good Example; ought not we to fly their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55678:14"/> who for the indulging their own Sottiſh Humour, teach us to neglect theſe Fundamental Duties, who ſee their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Children wanting Neceſſaries, the Poor Bread, and their Creditors ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling under the weight of many Miſeries, whilſt they are playing the Good-Fellows amidſt their Cups, and moſt wickedly throwing away that Mony with which they are bound to ſatisfie theſe Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions belonging to their Eſtate? Thus they Drink away the Comfort of their neareſt Relations, Swallow down the Bread of the Diſtreſs'd, the Blood of Orphans and Widows, and find a way by lifting up their Hands, to bring as certain Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion to themſelves and Friends, as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> did Deſtruction to his Enemies. And to it to be wonder'd now, why theſe are to be avoided by Chriſtians, theſe, who, help to caſt all Morality out of Doors, to make void all the Maxims of the Goſpel, and bring amongſt Men all that can be extravagant either of Folly or Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</p>
               <p>And if on theſe and many other weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Conſiderations, theſe Wet Chriſtians are baniſh'd the Company of all that are Good, have we not much more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55678:14"/> to conclude, they'll be baniſh'd the Society of the Bleſſed for ever? For if their Crimes render them ſo black and deteſtable, that they are unfit for the Converſation of the Juſt on Earth, how can we think of their being admitted into Heaven, where nothing that is De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed can enter? St. <hi>Paul,</hi> (as you have heard,) has ſaid it expreſly, that they ſhall <hi>not inherit the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">And S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> declares them to be moſt deteſtable in the Sight of God; and though ſome may think <hi>Drunkenneſs</hi> to be a light Sin, yet that whoever lies under the guilt of it, and does not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely repent and amend, ſhall be moſt certainly caſt out with Adulterers, and Murderers, and have his Portion with them in everlaſting Flames.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And if we ſriouſly conſider this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, what diſpoſition can we find in them for the Life of the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> who live here like <hi>Swine?</hi> Is the <hi>Bottle</hi> and the <hi>Pipe</hi> a Preparation for <hi>Happineſs?</hi> or are their Drunken and Filthy Songs, the way to tune their Souls for Allelujah's of Blifs? Chriſt commands his Followers to <hi>Deny themſelves,</hi> and is this Leſſon ſooneſt learnt in Ale-houſes and Taverns? Is <hi>Exceſs</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:55678:15"/> the way to <hi>Temperance?</hi> Is the <hi>Loſing thier Senſes</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> the means to <hi>put on Chriſt?</hi> Is the humouring their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Appetites, the way to <hi>Crucifie the Fleſh with the Affections and Luſts?</hi> Is Chriſt thus <hi>to be formed in them?</hi> Ah miſerable miſtaken Souls, that thus unhappily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves, who live in the open practice of Sin, are a Scandal to their Profeſſion, neglect their manifold Duties, and are even Tutors in Evil! What can they expect of Mercy, who have thus ſlighted all the means of Salvation? Or how ſhall Heaven be given them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be in reward of their Wickedneſs? No, <hi>they ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now what has here been ſaid, is not to be underſtood only of ſuch, as by exceſs of Drinking loſe their Reaſon and Senſes, but even of all thoſe who give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up to a Habit of Drinking, ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whole Days, or a conſiderable part of them, amidſt their Cups, though, through the ſtrength of their Brain, the Drink makes not the leaſt change in them: And therefore I muſt deſire theſe ſtronger Heads, not to flatter themſelves, as if Drinking were Innocent, as long as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55678:15"/> they find their Brains not diſtemper'd; for certainly, notwithſtanding this keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Wits, their Conſciences lie ſtill open to the Guilt of moſt grievous Sins, in the manifold breach of their Duty.</p>
               <p>And therefore, not inſiſting on the baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Brutal Entertainment, which is only in the Service of the Senſes, or to let them ſee how unmanly it is, to be ever Sipping, and dwell among Drink; how poor an Hononr it is to Drink the Company Dead; how unbecoming a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, to Swallow more Wine than the reſt, that is, of the whole Company to be moſt like a Hogſhead; I call their Thoughts at preſent to more weighty Conſiderations, and wiſh them to reflect how little better their caſe is, in regard to Chriſtianity and Heaven, than the worſt of Drunkards.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Let e'm remember, that however harmleſs they think this their Drinking Diverſion to be, the <hi>Word of God</hi> gives it another Character, and ſhews its ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence, by pronouncing <hi>Wo's</hi> againſt them them that follow it: <hi>Wo unto them that are Mighty to drink Wine, and Men of Strength to mingle Strong Drink,</hi> Iſa. 5. 22. Where 'tis not only thoſe are condemn'd, who by their Intemperance forfeit their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55678:16"/> Reaſon, but alſo ſuch as preſerve their Wits amidſt their Exceſſes; their ſhewing their <hi>Strength,</hi> being here cenſur'd as a Weakneſs, and their <hi>Ability</hi> marked out as a Folly: So that however they may pride themſelves as Men of Parts, and make ſport of the Company that's fall'n under the weight of their Liquor, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is here pronouncing Woes againſt them; ſentences them to Miſeries, and declares them the object of its Wrath.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If they take an exact ſurvey of their Conſciences, and make a Catalogue of their Sins, for which they muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable at the laſt day, I apprehend the difference between them and the moſt Sot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Drunkards, will not be very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: For 1. They muſt give an account of the waſte of God's <hi>Creatures;</hi> all that Drink which is beyond a <hi>Moderate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment,</hi> being a moſt Certain Abuſe, and contrary to the <hi>End</hi> for. which 'twas in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by the Providence of God. 2. Of the <hi>Waſte of Time,</hi> whilſt thoſe Hours which ought to have been employ'd in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of the many Obligations annexed to every ſtate, have been miſ-ſpent in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſs; and when they ſhould have been working out their Salvation in the Pious
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55678:16"/> Exerciſes of a Chriſtian Life, have been indulging their Paſſions, and taken as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Steps towards Hell, as they have drunk away Hours, which were given them for a better end. 3. Of the <hi>Waſte of Mony,</hi> the expence of their Intemperance; and this if we conſider the many legions of Sins that follow at the Heels of it, is in too many a Sin of the firſt Magnitude, and I fear of a very Damning Complexion. For how can thoſe Men anſwer it, who let their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates run out at the Tap? God has bleſſed them with a plentiful or at leaſt ſufficient being, and they are ſet over it as <hi>Stewards,</hi> by a prudent management, to Husband it for the good of their Family and poor Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, or for the benefit of the Publick; and inſtead of this care to improve and diſpoſe of it for its due ends, they prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally waſte and deſtroy it to feed their own corrupt Appetites and Vices. What will they ſay, when the Lord of all ſhall ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon them to appear, when he ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them to give an account of all the Mony an account of all the Mony they have thus ſpent, of the Eſtates they have ruin'd, of the Family they have brought to miſery, if not downright want and beggary? Theſe may go on thus
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55678:17"/> Drinking, and call it by the ſoft Names of <hi>Diverſion,</hi> or <hi>ſpending an Hour with a Friend;</hi> but 'tis certain their employment is nothing better than Sacrificing to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols; and however they may call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Chriſtians, the Scripture ſays what Chriſtians they are, a ſort that are <hi>worſe than Heathens.</hi> 4. If they conſider how much they impair their Health by their Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, how many Diſtempers they bring on themſelves, and often become their own Murderers; if they add to this the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sins of their Companions, who by their Example are drawn into Drink; for though they eſcape being Drunk them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, are not they to anſwer for Criminal Exceſſes of all thoſe who by their Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Company, were encouraged thus to make Beaſts of themſelves; as likewiſe for all the misfortunes of their Families, which from hence often take their riſe? And this Crime is much blacker again in ſuch, as knowing the ſtrength of their own Brains, ſet purpoſely to make others Drunk, accounting it their Victory to ſee others fall at their Feet: And is not this a barbarous Triumph, to rejoyce in the crimes of their Neighbours; firſt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray them to a moſt grievous Sin, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55678:17"/> then to make Sport of their Weakneſs? This is nothing better, than offering their Companions a Sacrifice to the Devil; and whenſoever they go about it, they ought to change their Phraſe, and inſtead of the Invitation of <hi>Come, will you drink a Bottle?</hi> they ought to ſpeak plain, and ſay, <hi>Come, will you go Sacrifice to Hell?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus 'tis evident how their Sins will riſe upon the enquiry; eſpecially if we add again to theſe, the many Lewd, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and Irreligious Diſcourſes, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd by this Drinking, and other Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations too frequent in theſe Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments, which if they were to be all writ on thoſe Walls betwixt which they are acted, would make too long and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a Liſt. And what a poor ſatisfaction muſt it then be to Men, tho they be not often Drunk themſelves, to find ſo many Crimes lie at their Door? Can they poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly think themſelves Innocent, who thus live almoſt buried in Sin? Or what fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour can they expect from him, who is the juſt Avenger of all Iniquity? Is it likely, that Life Eternal will be their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; or with the worſt of Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards to be caſt out into utter Darkneſs?</p>
               <p>Neither can the <hi>one</hi> ſort of Drinkers,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55678:18"/> or the <hi>other,</hi> be able to juſtifie themſelves, notwithſtanding all thoſe ſpecious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texts with which they pleaſe their own Fancies, and encourage themſelves in this Sin. For 1. If the end they pretend to Drink for, be <hi>Company</hi> or <hi>Good-Fellowſhip,</hi> is not this moſt unchriſtian, while they ſee ſo many Sins before them? Is not this to leave God for the ſake of Men? Is it not to joyn with others in offending God? Might not theſe, with as good reaſon Drink Poyſon, or go to Hell for Company? 2. If it be to <hi>make Merry,</hi> is it not a great Madneſs to make a Paſtime of that which is the ruin of a Mans Reaſon, his Eſtate, Family and Soul? A Man in a Phrenzy might make a Bonfire of all he is worth, and Merrily Drink it to Aſhes: But for Men of Reaſon to do it, unleſs they find a way to be Drunk before they Drink, is not eaſily to be imagin'd. 3. If it be for the <hi>putting away Cares;</hi> this is little better than renouncing all Religion and Goſpel; for there Chriſt invites all ſuch to him; <hi>Come to me, all ye that labour and are heavy loaden, and I will refreſh you;</hi> but theſe Men turning their Back on Chriſt, ſeek this refreſhment in the Bottle, and expect that from a little Drink, which is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55678:18"/> to be found no where truly but in God. Ah poor Chriſtians! and what a Deceitful Comfort is this, which only ſtifles your Cares, but does not cure them! It heaps on you daily new Miſeries, and by your abandoning God, makes your Temporal Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction become Eternal; that is, inſtead of giving Relief, makes it to be without end. 4. <hi>If it be for the paſſing time away;</hi> this is a moſt ſhameful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to thoſe that make this Plea, ſince there is no Man but what has or ought to have ſomething better then this vile Imployment. How many things are there, that may be done for the benefit of our ſelves or the Publick? How many ſorts of Study that are both Profitable and Ornamental? How great a work in the Maſtering our Paſſions, and Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our Spiritual affairs? So that whoever duly conſiders his own condition, need never complain for want of buſineſs. And here I cannot but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire our <hi>City,</hi> but chiefly the <hi>Country-Gentry,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect how unbecoming, nay, how ſcandalous a thing it is, that Perſons whom God has enabled with Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, with Leiſure and with Parts, and given them the opportunity of doing good in their Generations, to become eminent in their Families and Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood, and an honour to their Country, ſhould ſo lay aſide all thoughts of Honour and Goddneſs, as to give themſelves up to this unmanly entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Drinking, paſs their whole time in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journing from one <hi>Good Houſe</hi> to another, and have little better Diſcourſe, than <hi>Where the beſt Wine is? How well they were entertain'd the other Day; and where they ſhall meet to Morrow?</hi> So that whoever intends to live Soberly, muſt neceſſarily avoid their Acquaintance; and for to ruin a good Eſtate, Family, Health, Brain and Soul, a Man need ſeek no better Inſtructors than they. This is a point worthy of their moſt ſerious conſideration, and if every one
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55678:19"/> would undertake to reform one, they would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly be ſtil'd the true Fathers of their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and Promoters of the Publick Good. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As for ſuch as pretend to Drink upon the account of <hi>ſtriking up a Bargain,</hi> there may be Circumſtances as the the World goes, that may plead for the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of this Cuſtom; but then it muſt ever be with a due regard to Temperance; for when Men on this pretext fall into Exceſs themſelves, or deſign to over-reach their Neighbour, when ſoften'd with Drink, they'l prove I fear at the end but ill Traders, whilſt for ſuch petty Satisfaction or Gain, they evidently runt he hazard of Eternity. Now if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe, there are others who dare not live more Sober than their Neighbours, for fear of being <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd,</hi> theſe are a Cowardly ſort of Chriſtians, who cannot bear a Reproach for Chriſts ſake: And how will they bear one day, being denied by Chriſt, whom they have firſt denied? for he will moſt certainly be aſham'd of them, as they have been of him.</p>
               <p>Here then I deſire all Chriſtians to reflect on the Unreaſonableneſs and ill conſequence of this Swi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Vice, and for ſuch as have been guilty of it, to enter upon ſerious and firm Reſolutions of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. They muſt expect no ſmall difficulties in this Undertaking; but however, if they once become ſo Couragious as to reject all Temptations to this Sin in the beginning, and permit not themſelves to venture into the Company of Good Fellows, they'll ſoon be Maſters of themſelves, and remove that Bar which otherwiſe would have kept them out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <trailer>The next Sheet ſhall be <hi>of Gaming.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="colophon">
               <p>Printed for <hi>Sam. Crouch,</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Popes-head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Alley,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> 1692.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:55678:19"/>
            <head>THE Friendly Monitor. OF GAMING.</head>
            <div type="text">
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Recreation neceſſary, but eaſily abus'd, even by Good Men. Gameſters ought not to make their Diverſion a</hi> Buſineſs. <hi>The great Miſchiefs of Immoderate Gaming. Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Cards,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>on Sundays, Scandalous.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>IT would be very Unreaſonable to paſs the ſame Cenſure againſt <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming,</hi> as we have done in the Two former Papers againſt <hi>Curſing</hi> and <hi>Drunkenneſs;</hi> for theſe are ſo <hi>Evil</hi> in themſelves, that 'tis not eaſie to find
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55678:20"/> ſuch <hi>Circumſtances</hi> as can take off their Guilt, and excuſe them from being high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Criminal: Whereas <hi>Gaming</hi> in it ſelf is Innocent, and the only Evil it has, is in the <hi>Abuſe</hi> of it. So that it cannot be our buſineſs at preſent, abſolutely to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn it, but rather to lay down ſuch Cautions as may be neceſſary for the keeping it within its due bounds, and preventing ſuch <hi>Abuſes</hi> into which Man's Weakneſs is too apt to lead him, whilſt it runs him beyond thoſe <hi>Ends</hi> for which 'twas intended.</p>
               <p>We need not doubt therefore in the firſt place to ſay, that <hi>Recreations</hi> are in their kind neceſſary; for ſince neither our Minds nor Bodies are able to endure a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant toil or application to Buſineſs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome convenient intervals of Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or Refreſhment, we are hence oblig'd ſo far to give them breath and eaſe, as may fit them for the carrying on their greater Duties with new vigor and life. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all ſort of <hi>Lawful Games,</hi> are in their kind ſerviceable for the giving us this Refreſhment, hence they become not only warrantable, but may be in ſome man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner neceſſary, if attended with all their due circumſtances, as to Time, Place,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55678:20"/> Perſons, Buſineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But becauſe Man is too prone to abuſe the beſt of things, and work Miſchief to himſelf out of that which was deſign'd for his Good, and this being the caſe too frequently of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation</hi> or <hi>Games,</hi> not only in reſpect of Ill Men, but of Perſons otherwiſe exemplar and good, 'twill be very juſtifiable, if I point at ſome <hi>Conditions</hi> neceſſary to be obſerv'd by all thoſe well inclin'd Perſons who are deſirous to prevent theſe Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs and Abuſes in themſelves or others.</p>
               <p>Having therefore ſuppos'd, that no ſort of Games ought to be us'd for Recreation, but ſuch as are <hi>Lawful,</hi> it being moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming the Name of Chriſtian, for Men to take pleaſure in that which is diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to God, or injurious to their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; and moſt unreaſonable to place their Diverſion in what will one day prove their Rack and Torment: As to all <hi>Lawful Games,</hi> care ought to be taken.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That they be uſed ſo far only, as they may reaſonably ſerve to recreate and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Mind, and fit it for Buſineſs, but not to make a <hi>Buſineſs</hi> of them. Hence thoſe are very much to blame, who ſet their Affections ſo much on any ſort of Game, as to be ever ſolicitous and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:55678:21"/> how they may enjoy this Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, who put by other affairs of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, and make them yield to this; and when any thing happens ſo obſtinately croſs to their Deſigns, that it will not be put by, fail not to diſturb and vex them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and are out of Humour with all they Converſe with. Theſe I ſay, and all others of this kind, are very much to blame, ſince they ſhew their Affections to be miſplac'd, and their Heart to be corrupt and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd.</p>
               <p>For as to that rank of Men in the firſt place, whoſe Livelihood depends on their own Induſtry, and on the careful manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their affairs; is it not evident, that by thus ſetting their Affections too ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly on Gaming, they become at length careleſs of their Buſineſs, loſe many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous Opportunities, commit their Concerns to the diſcretion and care of <hi>Servants,</hi> who too often take after their Maſter, and can't tell why they ſhould be more mindful of his Buſineſs, than he is of his own; till by degrees, Trade failing, and the Expence encreaſing, all falls to ruin, and they who with moderate care might have liv'd comfortably, are forc'd through their ill management, to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55678:21"/> take a diſhonourable ſhelter, help to undo their Creditors, live Viciouſly, and at the end die Miſerably; tho too often they live long enough to ſee their Children reduc'd to an honourable Slavery, and ſome of them, 'tis likely, who have not courage to ſubmit to their Condition, expoſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and taking ill Courſes, as their defence againſt Want and Miſery, which ſeems too evidently to threaten them. There are too many Families, God knows, that owe their Ruin to this Intemperance of Gaming; and too many are brought to the <hi>High-way</hi> and the <hi>Stews,</hi> to ſeek for that Bread, which <hi>Gaming</hi> took out of their Mouths: And if Maſters of Eſtates, and Fathers of Families could but take a true Survey of but half the Miſchiefs that are occaſion'd by this Vicious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, they would be very jealous of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving themſelves any liberty in this kind, and careful not to let their <hi>Recreation</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their <hi>Buſineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence it may be eaſily concluded to be a thing of dangerous conſequence, to permit <hi>Gaming</hi> in <hi>Servants</hi> or <hi>Younger Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> of either Sex; for however innocent it may be, to take the Diverſion of an Hour at leiſure time with a Friend; yet,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55678:22"/> when under this pretext of Recreation, the love of any Game begins to ſteal up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and they become fond and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt for it, is it not to be fear'd, that it will inſenſibly grow into a Cuſtom? And then, how often happens it, that what thus crept upon them in their tender Age, gains ſtrength with their Years; and what was their <hi>Paſtime</hi> in their <hi>Youth,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes their <hi>Buſineſs</hi> in their <hi>Riper State?</hi> And is it not hence, that a great deal of irregularity and ill Husbandry takes its riſe; that having now Families and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of their own to manage, this ill Cuſtom gets the better of all; Play is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd before Duty; thoſe that have E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, run them out by degrees, and thoſe that have none, having labour'd many Days for a little ſupport for themſelves and their Family, upon a little Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, play it all away in an Hour? Is not this the Miſery and Madneſs we ſee too often in thoſe of a meaner Condition, where the Man fails not to take true pains all the Week, and when on Saturday Night the Good Woman is waiting for the return of her Mate, to bring home a Supply to keep the Pot going, behold he, Good Fellow, has call'd in by the way,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:55678:22"/> and reſolving to take the refreſhment of one <hi>Game</hi> and a <hi>Tankard,</hi> comes ſoon to the end of his Pay, and then goes jogging Home with the end of an old Tune to his Wife, and on this and her Credit ſhe is to feed on all the Week, with the ſlender hopes of next Saturdays bringing a better Return. From this III Husbandry it is, thoſe of this lower Sphere are over-run with Miſery and Want; hence ariſe many and laſting diſcontents within Doors, the Woman is fretful and peeviſh, the Good Man ſeeks for Peace abroad, and ſpends amongſt his Companions, what ſhould Feed his Family: And in the mean time the Children grow up, but like ſo many little Bears, without Care or Education, and help to fill the World not with Men but Brutes.</p>
               <p>But <hi>2dly,</hi> As to thoſe of a higher rank, whoſe Fortune is made to their Hands, they are likewiſe much to blame, if they give themſelves the liberty of exceſſive Gaming: For tho their plentiful Eſtate excuſes them from labouring for Bread, yet is it not an unpardonable Ingratitude in them, to make no better Return to Heaven for this Bleſſing? God has encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs'd them with Good things, and whilſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:55678:23"/> they behold others on every ſide toiling for neceſſaries, they ſit in the midſt of Plenty and Eaſe; and ſhould not that <hi>Leiſure</hi> and <hi>Time</hi> he has given them, be better imploy'd then in <hi>Gaming?</hi> It ought to be their care certainly to be able to give an account of the <hi>Talents</hi> entruſted with them, and ſo to improve their <hi>Time,</hi> as to be as much above their Neighbours in <hi>Vertue</hi> and all Chriſtian accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as they are in <hi>Eſtate.</hi> But inſtead of thus commendably advancing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to ſee them ſotting it over a Bottle, and daily throwing away ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny leiſure Hours in no better imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than of <hi>Cards</hi> and <hi>Dice,</hi> is ſo unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a Crime, that as it little ſuits with their Quality, and argues them to have but <hi>Narrow Souls,</hi> which are thus delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſuch petty Diverſions; ſo it is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeable to all the Maxims of Piety and Religion; and no queſtion but he whoſe daily toil has been at the <hi>Plow</hi> or the <hi>Spade,</hi> ſhall at the laſt day be found to have been better imploy'd than they. Would it not therefore be much more becoming their Condition, to apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſome more <hi>Honourable Exerciſe</hi> than this, to take delight in Beautifying
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55678:23"/> their Minds with the Knowledge of ſuch things as might benefit both themſelves and their Country; and, if they muſt divert themſelves for an hour, to take care they make not this Diverſion their Buſineſs: Since theſe alſo, like thoſe of a lower degree, having their Thoughts thus ill taken up, are too often brought to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect their Concerns, cauſe great Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents at home, play away the Comfort and Support of their Families, and leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Children without due Education, or Fortune anſwerable to their Quality, entail on them a certain Inheritance of Confuſion and Miſery to many Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Now whilſt theſe are very often the diſmal effects of this Exceſs, 'tis but too evident how neceſſary it is, in all Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, to obſerve this Caution, of not letting it ſeize on the Affections ſo much, as to grow into the Seriouſneſs of Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But becauſe there are many others, who keep that due guard on themſelves, as to be out of danger of drawing any of theſe extravagant Evils on their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and therefore think themſelves, in all their Gaming, to be without Reproof. I muſt here put theſe in mind, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55678:24"/> this their Care and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of themſelves, they may yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur a manifold Guilt, ſufficient to ſully that Innocence, which, they think, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companies them in all their Diverſions; and therefore, on their account, I here add another Condition they ought to have regard to, that is,</p>
               <p n="2">2. That in all their Gaming they ought to have that Care and Moderation, as not to occaſion any <hi>Diſorder</hi> in the Family where they play. To apprehend this Caution aright, 'tis neceſſary to reflect, that every <hi>Regular Family</hi> has ſet hours of <hi>Eating,</hi> of <hi>Praying,</hi> of <hi>Sleeping,</hi> &amp;c. and that a <hi>conſiderable Good</hi> of the Family de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on this <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> and due Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of this Order; for that every Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily is a kind of little Republick within Doors; and that as he muſt neceſſarily be look'd on as an Enemy to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, who, to ſatisfie his own privare Humour, brings Diſorder and Confuſion into the Government: So can he be no other than the Overthrower or Enemy of a Family, who, to pleaſe himſelf, takes no care what Diſorders he occaſions in it; and by this means brings it in ſome man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to reſemble Hell it ſelf; one part of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55678:24"/> the Deſcription of which place is, that it is <hi>without Order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this is not the utmoſt extent of this Evil; for beſides the diſcompoſing a Family, I apprehend 'tis often attended with very conſiderable Miſchiefs, and ſuch as is ſeldom in their Power to remedy, who thus indiſcreetly give the occaſion. And therefore, however theſe Perſons, it may be otherwiſe Religious and Juſt, ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple not at all the <hi>Practice</hi> of ſitting at Friends Houſes till Ten, Eleven or Twelve a Clock at Night at <hi>Cards, &amp;c.</hi> but go home after this, ſlattering themſelves, and ſaying, <hi>What Evil have we done? We have ſpent an hour in diverting our ſelves and our Friends: We have hazarded nothing more than we can well ſpare: We have wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no body; We have not fallen into Paſſion, neither curs'd nor ſwore, nor committed any Exceſs; and where's the harm of all this?</hi> Thus they may ſtate their own Caſe, and pleaſe themſelves with the fair proſpect of ſo much Innocence: Yet if the true ſtate of their Affairs were to be laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, I fear they muſt begin their reckoning again, and will find, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of ſo much Innocence, they have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the Guilt to anſwer for of tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all the Commandments.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:55678:25"/>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:55678:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:55678:26"/> I know they are ready to ask me, Where is the <hi>Theft, Murder</hi> and <hi>Adultery, &amp;c.</hi> in playing a Game at Cards? And I anſwer, If they find themſelves clear in their own Conſciences, I have nothing to ſay againſt them, as to their own <hi>Perſons:</hi> But then let them tell me, whether they have none of theſe, or ſuch like Sins, to anſwer for, in their <hi>Servants?</hi> Theſe ſee their Maſters ſpend, almoſt daily, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hours in Gaming, and are not ſenſible of any harm in their doing the like; hence by degrees they grow in love with Play, and having ſo many opportunities of Practiſing, become as they think, Maſters of the Art; ſo far, till at length they grow ill Husbands, Drinkers, Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Extravagant, and fall into all ſort of Vice: Now ſhall none of all this lie at their Maſters Door, who by their <hi>Ill Hours</hi> and <hi>Immodera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Diverſions,</hi> have given their Servants ſuch frequent <hi>Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of <hi>Idleneſs,</hi> and train'd them up in a method, fit for the learning all manner of Wickedneſs?</p>
               <p>But theſe Evils, it may be, come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind at ſo great a diſtance, that they may hope the Guilt falls not much on them: Let them look therefore on every Nights
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:55678:26"/> Work, and ſee whether nothing of this happens, for which they muſt be, in part, accountable. The Maſters are engag'd at their Game till late at Night; the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, who 'tis likely were well employed at their <hi>uſual Hours,</hi> now when theſe are paſt, have nothing to do; they meet together, and, if there be but one bad amongſt them, he ſets them on ſome idle Diſcourſe, every one takes their turn in telling their Maſters Faults, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame their Neighbours, repeat wicked Paſſages; and often immodeſt Stories and filthy Songs here take their place; here they teach and encourage one another in evil, and thoſe who brought with them pure and innocent Minds, ſoon find them corrupted: And who now muſt anſwer for the Tranſgreſſions of this Aſſembly? They muſt every one, 'tis true, hold up their Hands for themſelves; but ſhall not the <hi>Maſters</hi> too be brought in as <hi>Promoters</hi> and <hi>Encouragers,</hi> who by their <hi>ill Honrs</hi> lay before their Servants the <hi>occaſions</hi> of theſe Evils? Of theſe, I ſay, and often more than theſe: For when Servants have thus contracted a Familiarity, and finding Sleep now draw on with the Night, they grow weary of this Entertainment, the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:55678:27"/> Meeting is broke up by degrees, one lies down on a Bench, others retire into this Corner, others into that; and can any one tell me, whether the ill conſequences of this Privacy and Retirement, may not be much more pernicious than what was acted in Publick. Thus may this <hi>Innocent Gaming</hi> be eaſily attended with the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Crimes; and thoſe <hi>Maſters,</hi> who paſs under the Character of <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>Good,</hi> have Sins to anſwer for againſt all the Commandments, for not keeping due <hi>Order</hi> in their Diverſions.</p>
               <p>Since therefore there will be ſome <hi>Gaming,</hi> let him be <hi>my Man,</hi> who conſiders <hi>how much</hi> he may venture, and will play for <hi>no more;</hi> who thinks how <hi>much time</hi> may be proper for a reaſonable Diverſion, without giving any <hi>Diſturbance</hi> to the Family of his Friend or his own; and when that is expir'd, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Winner or Loſer, goes his way. And for the <hi>Maſter of a Family,</hi> let him be the <hi>Man,</hi> who, Brave as a Chriſtian ought to be, ſees this Order duly kept in his Houſe; who is Civil to his Friends, but Juſt to his Family; lets them know his Hours, and yields not from his Duty, in Complement to any ones Weakneſs; for this he can't do, without ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Weakneſs as great as theirs.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Third Condition to be obſerv'd by thoſe that Game at <hi>Cards</hi> or <hi>Dice</hi> is, <hi>That they Play not on Sundays:</hi> This is added for the ſake of ſome Perſons, who I am told, ſcruple not thus to divert themſelves on the Lord's Day, being of Opinion, there's no more guilt in <hi>this,</hi> than in any other ſort of Harmleſs Diverſion, ſuch as <hi>Walking</hi> or <hi>Diſcourſing.</hi> I meddle not here with the Lawfulneſs of the thing in it ſelf, but one thing I
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55678:27"/> with all aſſurance declare, that this ſort of Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Cards,</hi> &amp;c. on <hi>Sundays,</hi> is what gives great <hi>Scandal</hi> to others: And I think every good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ought to have that Tenderneſs towards his Neighbour, as not to give him occaſion of Offence on thoſe days on which all things ought moſt particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to be done to Edification. I know their Plea is, That if their Neighbour be Scandaliz'd at this, it proceeds from his <hi>Weakneſs,</hi> and not from any juſt occaſion given by them; and therefore, if there be any Fault, 'tis <hi>his</hi> and not <hi>theirs.</hi> I anſwer, were the caſe really thus, is it not ſtill a great Chriſtian Duty in matters of this nature, which no <hi>Neceſſity</hi> or <hi>Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> preſſes, to have regard to the <hi>Weakneſs</hi> of our Brother? St. <hi>Paul</hi> was ſo cautious and tender in a caſe like this, that he ſolemnly declares, If he ſaw his Brother thro' <hi>want of Knowledge</hi> or <hi>Weakneſs,</hi> offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at his eating of ſuch Meat, which he <hi>lawfully</hi> might<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yet on this conſideration, <hi>I will eat no Fleſh,</hi> ſays he, <hi>while the World ſtandeth,</hi> 1 Cor. 8. 13. For this reaſon, while he ſhews it to be no Sin to eat Meat offer'd to Idols, at the ſame time he deſires the Faithful to <hi>take heed leſt by any means they abuſe this Liberty, and become a Stumbling-block to them that are weak,</hi> v. 9. For that by <hi>ſinning againſt the Brethren, and wounding their weak Conſcience, they ſin againſt Chriſt,</hi> v. 12. If therefore <hi>Playing at Cards on Sundays,</hi> were as <hi>lawful</hi> as theſe Men pretend, yet ought they to take heed, <hi>not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe this Liberty,</hi> to the offence of thoſe Brethren, whoſe weak Conſciences are wounded by this Diverſion; and by this Moderation, prevent that Scandal, which they otherwiſe bring on their Church and Religion.</p>
               <p>Secondly, If they muſt have Diverſion on theſe Days, why ſuch an one as is ſo <hi>dangerous</hi> and ſubject to ſo many <hi>Abuſes,</hi> which even the Pious and Diſcreet have difficulty enough to uſe with Moderation, but too often fall into <hi>Exceſs,</hi> either as to the length of <hi>Time,</hi> or of <hi>Heat</hi> and <hi>Paſſion, Conteſting, Swearing,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55678:28"/> Covetouſneſs,</hi> &amp;c. And if there be any that can govern themſelves as to theſe Points, yet don't they by their Example encourage others at leaſt to Play, who cannot? And is this a good Sunday-work?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, How does this Diverſion agree with the Precept? God commands this Day to be <hi>kept Holy;</hi> and theſe Men ſpend a conſiderable part of it at Cards. What ſort of <hi>Chriſtian Holineſs</hi> is there in this? This Game would be a <hi>Prophanation</hi> of a <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Place,</hi> how comes it to be a means of <hi>Sanctifying a Holy Day?</hi> Methinks ſince God has reſerv'd but <hi>One</hi> Day of the <hi>Seven</hi> to himſelf, it might be much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter imploy'd; eſpecially too, ſince every Chriſtian beſides Praiſing and Adoring his Maker, has the great works of his Soul and Eternity to be done on that Day: The works of calling himſelf to an account, enquiring into the ſtate of his Soul, maſtering his Paſſions, regulating his Affections, repenting of his Sins, preparing for Death and Judgment, Reading, Inſtructing and Catechiſing thoſe under his Charge, whether Children. Servants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe may very well ſerve for a full employment for <hi>One day</hi> in the Week; and thoſe that find then time to <hi>Play at Cards,</hi> I fear know not the great work they have to do, or at leaſt leave it undone.</p>
               <p>There are ſome other Conditions I would have ſet down, but I think they may be reduced to theſe; and I cannot but hope, if Chriſtians would be exact in the obſervance of theſe mention'd, Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences and Evils might be avoided, which are too common amongſt Gameſters, and Men would find a way to give themſelves a juſt Diverſion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out entrenching on their Greater Duties, and Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away all Religion and Chriſtianity.</p>
               <trailer>The next ſhall be <hi>Of the Sin of Detraction.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="colophon">
               <p>Printed for <hi>Sam. Crouch,</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Popes-head-Alley,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal-Exchange,</hi> 1692.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:55678:28"/>
            <head>THE Friendly Monitor. Of the SIN of DETRACTION.</head>
            <div type="text">
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Speaking ill of our Neighbour</hi> a Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Charity, againſt the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, againſt Juſtice, Fidelity and Truth. Too frequent in the Converſation of both Sexes. Some Directions on this Subject.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>BY <hi>Detraction</hi> I underſtand that Sin, by which Men leſſen and impair the Credit of their Neighbour, either by Whiſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, by Falſe Reports, Stories taken up upon truſt, weak Surmizes, and even the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:55678:29"/> diſcovering of ſuch Truths, as betray his Infirmities, and evidently prejudice his Reputation. Now this being a Sin, which has over-run the geateſt part of Mankind, and invaded the Tongues even of thoſe, who amongſt Men, bear the Character of <hi>Good, Pious</hi> and <hi>Juſt,</hi> I think 'tis but reaſonable, it ſhould be expos'd in its Colours, that ſo the Foulneſs and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity of it being laid open, it may be deteſted by the Good, and excluded the Converſation of all thoſe, who look to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven, and think of having a part in the Reſurrection of the Juſt.</p>
               <p>For this end we need only conſider, that <hi>Speaking to the diſcredit of others,</hi> is a Sin, not level'd only againſt ſome Branch of the Commandments, but even againſt one of thoſe main <hi>Pillars,</hi> on which the whole Law depends, that is, the <hi>Love we owe our Neighbours:</hi> And whilſt it overthrows this, it likewiſe undermines the other; ſince he that <hi>loves not his Neighbour,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives himſelf, if he thinks he <hi>loves God:</hi> So that, tho it be but a ſhort, yet 'tis a clear Caſe, that <hi>He that ſpeaks evil of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> has neither the <hi>Love of God,</hi> nor of his <hi>Neighbour</hi> in his Heart. And what a Chriſtian muſt he be, who thus, in one
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:55678:29"/> Act, tramples on the whole Law of God, and leaves his Soul void of all Spiritual Life? The Life of Charity, I mean, which is the <hi>Bond of Perfectneſs, and the end of the Commandments,</hi> and without which God can neither abide in us, nor we in him.</p>
               <p>'Tis not therefore ſufficient for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to preſerve himſelf from thoſe more notorious and infamous Crimes, of Idolatry, Drunkenneſs, Fornication, Steal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but from this of <hi>Detraction</hi> and <hi>Backbiting</hi> too: For however this be not altogether ſo ſcandalous, and of ſo black a Complexion in the Eyes of Men, as the former; yet 'tis equally deſtructive in it ſelf, of all Goodneſs, as deteſtable in the ſight of God, and as certainly damns thoſe that are guilty of it, as any of the reſt; for 'tis the Spirit of God has ſaid it by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> That not only <hi>Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cators, Idolaters, Adulterers, Drunkards, &amp;c.</hi> but <hi>Revilers</hi> alſo <hi>ſhall not inherit the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 9, 10.</p>
               <p>Is it not therefore a Caution indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſably neceſſary for all that profeſs Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, to look ſomething beyond that narrow Scheme of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> which the Phariſee in the Goſpel fram'd to himſelf, and went home contented? For what if,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:55678:30"/> like him, they are not Extortioners, nor Unjuſt, nor Adulterers? What if they Faſt and Pray, and give Alms? Will not all this come far ſhort of Heaven, if with him over-looking their own Faults, they ſeverely <hi>cenſure</hi> and <hi>condemn</hi> their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour? Will Faſting and Praying take off the guilt from this uncharitableneſs? Or will <hi>not being an Extortioner,</hi> or an <hi>Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer,</hi> make <hi>Detraction</hi> Innocent? No, this one Sin is ſufficient to pollute the pureſt Soul; it renders even the beſt of Chriſtian Exerciſes fruitleſs; and though there be an exact compliance with all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Duties, yet is not all this ſufficient to prevent the diſmal effects of this Vice. For tho' a Man ſhould have all Faith, ſo as to remove Mountains, and have no Charity, he is nothing: Tho he beſtows all his Goods, and feeds the Poor; tho he gives his Body to be burnt, and has not Charity, it profits him nothing.</p>
               <p>Thus ſtands it then with this Vice of <hi>Back-biting, Reviling,</hi> and <hi>ſpeaking ill of others,</hi> in regard of God and Eternity; for whilſt it diveſts a Man of the Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Garment of <hi>Charity,</hi> it certainly marks him out for one whoſe unavoidable Fate will be, to be caſt forth into utter
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:55678:30"/> Darkneſs. And if we conſider it now a little more particular in it ſelf, we ſhall ſtill diſcover the unreaſonableneſs of it, and other Motives to deteſt it.</p>
               <p n="1">For 1. Is not this a Sin directly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit to that Principle of Nature, of <hi>doing as we would be done by?</hi> Let but any one examin his own Heart, and ſee how he is affected, when he hears of any that makes Reflections on his Words or Actions, or reports ſuch things, as any ways ſeem to prejudice his Reputation. Does not this touch a Man to the quick, raiſe a diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance within him, and often ſtir up ſo much Gall and Bitterneſs, that with ſome Tempers, 'tis not in the power of Time or Friends to make them think well of ſuch Perſons any more? A <hi>Good Name, Credit</hi> and <hi>Reputation</hi> are tender things, and there's no touching them ſo lightly, but we are preſently ſenſible, and often think our ſelves deeply wounded even with a Glance, that elſewhere would not be enough to race the Skin.</p>
               <p>And is it not then a ſtrange ſort of an unnatural Crime in Men, to make their Neighbours Faults the common Subject of their Entertainment, to be ſporting with ſuch Diſcourſes as blemiſh and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:55678:31"/> wound their Reputation; whereas if the Scale were but turn'd, and their Neighbours were but doing the like of them, they would not bear it without Indignation; their preſent Smiles would be changed into Frowns, and they that make it a Paſtime in commenting on the Failings of others, would find it to be quite otherwiſe, when their own Faults were call'd over? Muſt not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe Perſons, who accuſtom themſelves to this ſort of Vice be of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unthinking Temper, ill-natur'd, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate and raſh, who thus deal with their Neighbour, ſo far otherwiſe, than they would be done by?</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2ly.</hi> 'Tis a Vice contrary to Juſtice, Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity and Truth. For I think 'tis a thing not to be denied, that ſuch as are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in medling with their Neighbours Concerns, and diſcourſing of their Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſights and Imperfections, very often relate ſuch things for Truths, which are not ſo. They take up Paſſages upon <hi>Hear-ſays</hi> and <hi>Reports,</hi> and then tell them for <hi>Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;</hi> whereas there's nothing more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, than that the greateſt parts of thoſe Reports are uncertain. Let but any Man reflecton what has happen'd to himſelf in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:55678:31"/> this kind, of the many Miſtakes he has ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in himſelf and others; and if his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience be any thing anſwerable to mine, I think he may, without raſhneſs, venture a conſiderable Wager, that of all the Stories he hears relating to Third Perſons, there's not One in Ten exactly according to Truth. 'Tis but ſounding a thing to the bottom, and we ſhall ſeldom fail of finding more or leſs than what is told. Paſſion and Prejudice often creep in and diſguiſe the Truth; ſome make Additions out of a vicious Habit, and having un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to relate a Paſſage, help it out with the laying on of ſuch Colours and Circumſtances, as may make it grateful to the Company, and worth their hearing; ſo that they ſcruple not to venture their Neighbours Credit, for the gaining them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a little Applauſe, or the raiſing a Smile or Surprize in thoſe they entertain. How often is it, that Men mix their own <hi>Conſtructions</hi> and <hi>Comments</hi> with thoſe matters of <hi>Fact</hi> they undertake to relate; and then another that is not very diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, runs away with the <hi>Whole,</hi> and tells it to the next Company for the exact Truth, and nothing but the Truth? And are there not many, who pretend to inform you of <hi>what ſuch an one ſaid at
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:55678:32"/> ſuch a time; of what hapned betwixt ſuch a Man and his Wife, Children, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> &amp;c. And whilſt they give you the aſſurance of telling you nothing, upon their Words, but what they heard and ſaw, leave out the particular <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> or <hi>Occaſions</hi> of what was ſaid or done, and make the thing as unlike what it was in it ſelf, as if they had fram'd it all in their own Heads? Thus, whether by Miſtake, Inadvertency, or on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, there are but few Paſſages come to us, but they are firſt diſguis'd or corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome of theſe ways; eſpecially if they come by Second and Third Hands; for then certainly, like Waters that run through Minerals, they receive a Tincture, according to the <hi>Affection, Vanity, Weakneſs</hi> or <hi>Lightneſs</hi> of the Parties, that help'd to convey them to us.</p>
               <p>And while Matters ſtand thus, do not all thoſe deal very unjuſtly with their Neighbours, who freely diſcourſe of their Imperfections, and help to hand down Stories, which are to their Diſcredit; ſince 'tis a plain caſe, they often put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves on relating ſuch things for <hi>certain,</hi> of which they are ſo far from <hi>knowing,</hi> that they have rather reaſon to <hi>queſtion</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:55678:32"/> the Truth? And tho' the things were really true; yet whilſt there is ſo much reaſon to doubt of it, they are unjuſt and unfaithful to their Neighbours in as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny caſes as they contribute to the leſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Reputation by ſuch Relations.</p>
               <p>But laſtly, tho it be more certain, that many Perſons are really guilty, both in <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Actions,</hi> of things <hi>Raſh, Fooliſh, Wicked, Prophane,</hi> &amp;c. Yet is it not war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable, even for thoſe who moſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly know the Truth, and were Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of ſuch Extravagancies, to make relations of them to Third Perſons; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, notwithſtanding all this Truth and Certainty, 'tis poſſible, nay, often likely, they may be yet very unjuſt to the Parties concern'd in ſo doing. For how often happens it, if we may favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably judge of others by our ſelves, that Men ſpeak and do ſuch things as are really very fooliſh and indiſcreet, and commit great Overſights and Errors; and it may be, the Words are no ſooner ſpoke, or the things done, but on the firſt Reflection, they are vex'd, and, within their own Breaſts, reprehend themſelves, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as much at their being thus overſeen, and condemn it as ſeverely as any of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:55678:33"/> By-ſtanders? Now for a Third Perſon, in theſe caſes, to go and whiſper, or tell openly to others, the Paſſages of ſuch Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies or Indiſcretions, is certainly moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt; ſince, by theſe Relations, they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print ſuch Characters and Idea's in the Minds of the Hearers, that in reality be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long not to the Perſons of whom they ſpeak; but theſe are as certainly wrong'd in their Reputation, as a Man would be in his Features, who by ſome Accident turning his Mouth awry, or skrewing up his Noſe, ſhould have a Painter take him in that nick, and tranſmit his Picture to Poſterity under all thoſe Deformities.</p>
               <p>And in other caſes, of Men that are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly ſcandalous, whoſe Follies are as publick as their Perſons, 'tis many times not without treſpaſſing againſt Juſtice, that their Crimes are brought into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Diſcourſes. For does not God often touch the Hearts of ſuch Sinners, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually withdraw them from all their Errors, ſo that there's nothin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt more, than the Diſorders of their paſt Life? And now, for ſuch as have thus happily obey'd the Call of Heaven, and by a ſincere Repentance and Change of Life, made their Peace with God, is it
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:55678:33"/> not very unreaſonable and unjuſt, that their Crimes ſhould be yet kept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live among Men, and they expos'd, to their reproach, at Table-Entertainments and Viſits? God has forgot and forgiven their Sins, but not ſo their good Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and Friends; but theſe ſtill ſhew them under all the Horror of Filth and Pollution, when in the ſight of God they are ſpotleſs, innocent and pure. And can this be done without the Imputation of a great Injuſtice, thus in fact, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe the Sentence of Heaven, and to make them ſtill Criminals here, who are diſcharged above? And if this be the caſe of all thoſe, who revive in Company the Extravagancies of ſuch as are truly reclaim'd; is it not very dangerous at any time to enter upon this Subject of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Follies? For who can tell, but the Party, however formerly guilty, has ſince repented? There may be Preſumptions, but hardly an aſſurance of the contrary; and may it not then eaſily be, that the Perſons thus reproach'd, may notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all their paſt Crimes, by an hearty Repentance, be receiv'd into the Favour of God, and become Stars in Heaven; when thoſe who ſpeak Evil of them, for
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:55678:34"/> their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs</hi> and <hi>Injuſtice</hi> may find themſelves caſt out and be miſerable for ever?</p>
               <p>And now, ſince <hi>ſpeaking of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour's Failings</hi> is in its ſelf ſo dangerous, that it cannot be eaſily ſeparated from Sin: For if the Subject of the Diſcourſe be any thing that is <hi>Falſe</hi> or <hi>Doubtful,</hi> it is a certain Offence againſt <hi>Juſtice,,</hi> and if it be <hi>True,</hi> it may be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njust</hi> ſtill, but is unavoidably a Breach of Chriſtian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Is it not a great Pity, that this ſort of Diſcourſe ſhould be ſo frequent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, that there cannot be two or three together one half hour, but ten to one this is made a part of their Entertainment? And if this were the Weakneſs only of thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, who give themſelves up to Liberty and Vice, and whoſe Life is a Scandal to their Profeſſion, it were not much to be admir'd: For what wonder is it, for thoſe who live ill, to ſpeak ill too; and to find them both in <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> all of a piece? But the miſery is, that even thoſe who are of a more regular Life, who have an Horror of whatſoever ſeems Criminal, who war againſt Sin, and by the exerciſes of Piety ſeem ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:55678:34"/> to pretend to Heaven, are yet over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken in this Snare, as freely begin and help on theſe Diſcourſes, as if there were nothing in them contrary to Piety and Religion. This is the Complaint of an Ancient Father long ago: <hi>There are few,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that are free from this Vice, and that live ſo without Reproof, as to ſcruple the laying open their Neighbours Faults: So that even thoſe, who have an Abhorrence of other Sins, live in the open Practice of this.</hi> And is not this a great Overſight and kind of Stupidity, that thoſe well inclin'd Souls, whoſe Thoughts and Deſires ſeem to be ſo fix'd on Heaven, as to be exact in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every Duty, ſhould ſail in this one? That their own Lives ſhould be almoſt blameleſs, and out of an itch of talking, to incur the Guilt of other Mens? To live in the way of Heaven, and talk themſelves to Hell, and be damn'd for their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Crimes, is certainly very ill manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and an Indiſcretion of a moſt fatal conſequence.</p>
               <p>And while it is an Evil thus foul and impious, is it not again a matter both of pity and wonder, that it ſhould have inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated its ſelf ſo far into the Favour of that more pious and tender Sex, as to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:55678:35"/> become faſhionable in their moſt Friendly <hi>Viſits,</hi> and to be one of the Topicks of their daily Converſation? To hear them diſcourſe of Faſhions and Dreſſes, of Jewels, Balls, Coaches, Watches, Air, Weather, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is a ſuitable and becoming Entertainment; but when they ſummon in abſent Neighbours, and every one take their turn ſlinging at them, in diſcovering their Imperfections, in calling over their Follies and Vices, in telling their Hear-ſays and Gueſſes, in blackning their Reputation, and even murthering them in <hi>Eſſigie;</hi> here, methinks, they ſeem to forget themſelves, and go beyond the Moderation reaſonably to be expected from the tenderneſs of their Sex, and Piety of their Education.</p>
               <p>For my part, when I conſider a Man's Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections and Failings, they ſeem to me as ſo many <hi>Sores</hi> and <hi>Wounds</hi> in his Soul; and when I look on his <hi>Vices</hi> and <hi>Sins,</hi> what are they, but ſo much <hi>Stench, Filth</hi> and <hi>Pollution?</hi> Now is it not very unbecoming in this Sex, to be opening their Neighbours <hi>Wounds</hi> with their <hi>Tongues;</hi> to be licking at his Sores; and when they take ſo much care in perfuming themſelves, to be ſo eaſie in turning up a Dunghil, to dwel in Sinks, and be raking in them ſo long, till they ſend a Stench up to Heaven? It would certainly be much more commendable in them, as likewiſe in all others, to take more after the <hi>Good Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> in the Goſpel, and as often as, like him, they
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:55678:35"/> behold their Neighbour wounded in his Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to expreſs towards him a Chriſtian Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs and Compaſſion, and to ſtrive by all the Lenitives and healing methods, to cloſe up his Wounds: To put in a Word to excuſe his Weakneſs; to take off ſomething of the Guilt, by ſuppoſing ſome <hi>Miſtake</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty</hi> in the Relation; and if nothing elſe can be done, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Company's Eyes at leaſt from ſo foul an Object, by ſtarting a more charitable Diſcourſe. But in ſtead of this, to be diverted in adding to his Misfortunes, to find ſport in having a hand in his Sores, and taring open his Wounds, when, 'tis likely, they were almoſt skin'd over and heal'd, is a ſort of Spiritual Cruelty, not agreeable to any, but ſuch whoſe Nature is almoſt Barbarous, and who are near to <hi>Cannibals</hi> in Religion.</p>
               <p>What then is to be done by thoſe, who deſire to avoid this Evil; for it ſeems to be ſo common in all Converſation, that a Man muſt decline all Company that deſires to eſcape its Conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? 'Tis neceſſary in the firſt place, for every one to begin at home, and effectually to take care, to cut off all ſuch vicious Liberty in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſo as to reſolve neither to begin, nor help on a Diſcourſe that reflects on any Neighbour. But becauſe a Guilt may be here contracted by <hi>Hearing,</hi> as well as <hi>Speaking,</hi> a diligent Care is to be us'd in this point, tho ſomething different according to the Quality and Circumſtances of the Perſons in whoſe Company we are, and who carry on ſuch Diſcourſes.</p>
               <p>If they are ſo far our <hi>Betters,</hi> that to reprove them would ſavour of Arrogance or Raſhneſs, we ought to be careful not to take any Delight,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:55678:36"/> nor ſhew any Satisfaction in what they ſay, nor by Smiles to flatter them in their Calumnies; but rather to quit their Company, if it may be; or expreſs ſome Diſlike, at leaſt, at their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neighbourly Entertainments. But if they are ſuch, with whom we may freely take the liberty of ſpeaking, what ſhould a Chriſtian do, on theſe occaſions, but become his Neighbours Advocate, make the Beſt Plea for him the Cauſe will bear, queſtion the Evidence, which however poſitive, is very often accompanied with Miſtakes or Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? And if it be undeniable, bid thoſe who are Innocent fling the firſt Stone at him. Enquire who made us Judges over our Brethren, who are too often in the ſame Condemnation; and if we are not, by whoſe Favour is that? Turn the Diſcourſe out of Doors, expreſs a Zeal for thy Abſent Neighbour, as if it were thy own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, ever remembring how good thy Cauſe is, whilſt in this thou fighteſt the Battles of thy Lord; for it is he has ſaid it, Whatever is done to any of his little ones, is done to him. Oh, how were it to be wiſh'd, that Men would be careful to follow this Rule, <hi>Never to ſpeak nor bear ill of their Neigbours!</hi> How many Bleſſings might we expect upon ſuch a Reformation! How many Souls would be made happy! 'Tis by Charity we abide in God, and God in us. And as the Breach of Charity is a Sin againſt the Greateſt Precept, ſo it muſt certainly be the moſt Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of all.</p>
               <trailer>The next ſhall be <hi>Of Immodeſty.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="colophon">
               <p>Printed for <hi>Sam. Crouch,</hi> at the Corner of <hi>Popes-head-Alley,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal-Exchange,</hi> 1692.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:55678:36"/>
            <head>THE Friendly Monitor. Of the SIN of IMMODESTY.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>'Tis a dangerous Vice, and requires a ſtrict Guard on all the Senſes for its Cure. The great Miſchiefs of Immodeſt Gazing, of Immodeſt Books and Pictures, of lewd Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lads, Plays and Romances. Immodeſt Diſcourſe and Filthy Songs turn Chriſtians into Devils; the Miſchiefs they do are ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reparable, how difficult then muſt their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance be!</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THis Vice in its whole extent, is ſo foul and contagious, that there's no <hi>Thinking of it</hi> without danger; <hi>Writing of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:55678:37"/> it</hi> is much more pernicious; and <hi>Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it,</hi> would be accompanied with evils ſtill worſe, and more fatal to all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Chriſtianity. And yet, whilſt it is become ſo Epidemical, that it has infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the greateſt part of mankind, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, it ought not to be paſs'd by Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſur'd, but rather deſerves the ſevereſt Condemnation, in as much as the Evils, it carries with it, are, above all Vices, more Dangerous and Univerſal. Since therefore it ſeems juſt, I ſhould oppoſe it, I think it ſafeſt to follow the Method of War, in regard of thoſe Strong Holds, which are fortified by nature and are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceſſible, that is, block up all the Ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues and Paſſes, and ſo bring them to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, without expoſing the Beſiegers to that hazard, which a nearer approach would neceſſarily oblige them to.</p>
            <p>Thus, while I make War againſt this Vice, will I keep at a diſtance, for ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſervation, and make it my whole endeavour to poſſeſs my ſelf of all it Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that is, of all the <hi>Senſes,</hi> which are ſo many <hi>Ways,</hi> by which all Supplies and Succors are convey'd to it, for its Support and Strength; and if I can but ſecure theſe, this Evil muſt be weakn'd by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:55678:37"/> and will infallibly fall of it ſelf.</p>
            <p>The firſt Paſs or Senſe I deſire to ſecure, is that of the <hi>Eyes,</hi> which being the moſt Active of all the reſt, and conveying Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon into the Soul at the greateſt diſtance, is that which calls for our firſt care. And therefore as <hi>Job,</hi> making a ſolemn Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of his Integrity in ſeveral Duties, ſets the regulation of his <hi>Eyes</hi> in the front, <hi>I have made a Covenant with my Eyes, Job.</hi> 31. 1. So is it neceſſary for every Chriſtian, that ſincerely deſires to be faithful to his Duty in this point, to ſet a guard upon his <hi>Eyes,</hi> and deny them much of that liberty they are too prone to take, to ſatisfie themſelves, and that Corrupt Nature, which they ſerve. So that hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing duely conſider'd the true End, for which Our Creator deſig'nd theſe <hi>Lights,</hi> to <hi>Guide, Direct, Inform, Inſtruct</hi> us in all thoſe Particulars, which are helpful towards our Spiritual or Temporal Good, we are after this to reflect on the infinite ways they may be abus'd, and made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental towards the bringing the Soul into diſorder, confuſion and darkneſs; and here a ſhort view will ſerve to inform us, how many ways, and how often it is neceſſary to apply the firſt Maxim of our
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:55678:38"/> Lord, <hi>Of denying our ſelves,</hi> to this one Senſe of our Eyes, eſpecially in regard of this evil, which is our preſent Subject. For is not our Infirmity ſuch, that where-ever we go, whether for Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, Company, Diverſion, nay for Buſineſs and Devotion too, whereſoever we walk, we ever ſtand expos'd, and are under a neceſſity of keeping a ſtrict Watch upon this Senſe, for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of that interior Peace, which is the life of the Soul? And is it not the want of this care, that lays the Heart open to many dangerous Aſſaults of the Enemy, whereby ſo much of the World and its vain Delights creep in, as to leave but little room for Vertue and Religion, nay even to drive God quite out from thence? So that as a ſmall Neglect in this point ſeldom fails of filling the Soul with Diſturbance and Diſtraction, ſo 'tis moſt certain, the indulging of any Liberty in this kind, cannot end but in Vice.</p>
            <p>Hence they are ſeverely to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd, who whether in <hi>Company,</hi> or <hi>Walking the Streets,</hi> allow themſelves the Liberty of <hi>fixing their Eyes</hi> on every one they meet, that carries with them, either
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:55678:38"/> in their Face or Dreſs, any thing of Comelineſs or Beauty: And as many as they out-walk, that ſhew any thing of agreeableneſs in their Meen, cannot paſs them by without <hi>turning back</hi> and ſtaring them in the Face, to their own Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the practice of ſuch a <hi>Licentious Confidence;</hi> and the Scandal of the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Standers, who ſee them wilfully expoſing themſelves to what St. <hi>Paul</hi> has mark'd out as Unbecoming and Infamous in a Chriſtian, that is, the <hi>Luſt of the Eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe, I ſay, are ſeverely to be condemn'd: For ſince the condition of Man, in order to Eternity and Salvation, by the Divine appointment, is ſo difficult, and the Way ſo narrow, that it requires all the Diligence and Care a man can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly uſe; and having done his beſt, is ſtill to go on with <hi>Fear and Trembling;</hi> is it not a ſtrange Stupidity and Madneſs, to ſee Men making the Way ſtill narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, induſtriouſly encreaſing to themſelves new Difficulties, wilfully putting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into innumerable Hazards, and taking pains to ſeek ſtill more Enemies, when, if the truth were known, they have already more than they know how to maſter? Are not the Occaſions of Evil,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:55678:39"/> that are unavoidable, too many, that Men ſhould thus look for more? And is not the Devil buſy enough in his Snares, that Men ſhould thus turn Devils to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and become their own Tempters? Well may Satan reſt and not buſy himſelf with theſe; for they are forward enough to get his work done to his hand, and ſeem reſolv'd to have it all of their own doing: Why ſhould they elſe take up this ill Cuſtom, ſo often ſtop and put themſelves into thoſe dangers, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe are paſſing by them? Whoever therefore deſires ſeriouſly to ſecure himſelf againſt this Vice or maſter it, muſt take care to keep ſuch a ſtrict Guard on his <hi>Eyes,</hi> as, whether in <hi>Street</hi> or <hi>Company,</hi> to deny them this dangerous Liberty; it being, for the moſt part, by theſe Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows that Sin and Death enter into the Soul.</p>
            <p>There is ſtill a farther care neceſſary for this Senſe, and that is, the avoiding all Immodeſt <hi>Books, Pictures</hi> or <hi>Shews;</hi> theſe being as ſo many Snares of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, by which Innocence is Corrupted, evil Inclinations are ſtrengthn'd and fed, and the heart of man inflam'd with the fire of Hell: So that this Enemy of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:55678:39"/> cannot deſire to be ſecurer of any prey, than to ſee Men bite at any of theſe Baits. For is it not evident, that, whoſoever purpoſely reads any of theſe Books, is ſtudying the black Art, is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving himſelf in the Science of Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, becomes the Devils Scholar, and, under his Diſcipline, is learning to make war againſt Heaven? Is it not by ſuch like <hi>Pictures</hi> and <hi>Shews,</hi> the Thoughts are poſſeſs'd with evil, the Heart's carried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all that is foul and ſinful, and takes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in what it is ſtrictly bound to abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and deteſt? And while they are thus pernicious, ought it not to be every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy's care that is in love with Virtue, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to avoid them, as the Incentives to all ſort of Uncleanneſs? And for this end, would not all Maſters of Families diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge a great Duty, in having a watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Eye over all under their care, and not to permit amongſt them ſuch Books or Pictures, but ſeverely to chaſtiſe thoſe, who ſhall be found in this point delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent? For whilſt they pretend to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Education, and to be the Children of God, ought not they to be puniſh'd, as falſe to their Principles, who, by any of theſe Ways, profeſſedly hold a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:55678:40"/> reſpondence with the Devil? And were it not to be wiſh'd, that every Chriſtian Government would ſo far take notice of this Evil, as by Penalties, to endeavour the reforming of as much of it as is Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick? For is it not a ſhame, that filthy and immodeſt Prints and Pictures ſhould be permitted to be hung up on Walls, and there publickly expos'd for ſale; where they are an Offence to the Good, corrupt the Innocent, and are a Snare to the Unwary? where they ſerve to teach <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Youth</hi> to be <hi>Men</hi> in Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs betimes, and give them an early knowledge of what is ever learned too ſoon? Is it not pity, that theſe ſort of Books too ſhould be allow'd which are thus inſtructive in Sin, and teach that Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which every Good Body deſires to unlearn? Me-thinks, when I conſider, that we are Subjects of God, as well as of our King, theſe Books, which contain ſo much Treaſon againſt Heaven, ſhould be with as much care ſuppres'd, as Libels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Government; ſince Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ought no more to tolerate theſe deſigns againſt Heaven, than Loyalty do's againſt the State. And 'twere to be wiſh'd, that thoſe, who throughout Chriſtendom, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintend
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:55678:40"/> the ſpiritual Affairs, would ſo far ſtand up for Vertue, and maintain its Rights, as not to ſee it overthrown by the permiſſion of ſuch Contraband Goods as theſe. But however this be, 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, as many as trade in them, ought to look on themſelves no better than the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil's Factors; for tho' they get ſo much <hi>per Cent</hi> in their Sale, yet the <hi>Principal Gain</hi> is for Hell, whether they help to pack off more Souls 'tis likely than they have Pence come to their ſhare.</p>
            <p>But of this kind of Merchandiſe, I think, there's none worſe, than that, which is <hi>Book and Picture</hi> all in one, <hi>lewd Ballads,</hi> I mean, which, being every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy's Mony, ſeems contriv'd on purpoſe to convey filth into every Corner, to teach Children to be Vicious, as ſoon as they can read, and furniſh every Servant that has but an Half-penny to ſpare, with Wickedneſs enough to become chargeable to their Maſters, and in the end, to ruin themſelves. And that none may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of this knowledge, for want of Mony, 'tis but ſtanding one half hour under a Wall, and they may read half a dozen for nothing; nay, and for thoſe too that cannot read, they have ill luck if
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:55678:41"/> they meet not ſome of theſe in their walks, ſet off with an excellent New Tune, where they have Muſick into the bargain, to recommend and help down the Poyſon. Now to me it ſeems a thing altogether unwarrantable, that when two or three debauched Rimers have, over a Pot, botch'd up a filthy Song, which without <hi>Wit</hi> or <hi>Senſe,</hi> is juſt fitted to pleaſe nothing above the Beaſt in Man, they ſhould be permitted to publiſh theſe their Peſtiferous Thoughts in Print and Picture, and have them paſs for Current, as if <hi>enter'd according to order;</hi> when they are fit to appear no where, but in the region of Darkneſs, to feed that Fire, which will be their Torment, who prepare ſuch Fuel: And then for others of the ſame lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to go about ſtreets and tune out theſe infernal Lays in the midſt of unthinking Crowds and ſet up theſe Walking Bawdy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes at every Corner, nay and under the very Church Walls too, in defiance of that Goſpel, which is there preach'd, as if they meant nothing leſs than to undo all the Sunday Lectures with a Song, is a thing intolerable, and ſo oppoſite to all Religion and Goodneſs, that till the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick ſhall think fit to expreſs its Zeal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:55678:41"/> it, 'tis but neceſſary every private Perſon ſhould decline all ſuch Aſſemblies, where there's no approaching but at the expence of Modeſty and Shame, and the Scandal of all that are Good, who know, that after all the Sport and Noiſe, there's nothing elſe meant, but the Cheap Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of, <hi>Who'll learn to go to Hell for a Halfpenny?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There's too much of this ſort of Infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on too in <hi>Romances</hi> and <hi>Plays,</hi> tho' ſet off here in a much better Dreſs, which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders them ſtill the more dangerous in as much as thoſe Ingenious Covers of Wit, with which the Poyſon is there gilded, helps to carry it down with more eaſe and delight, and to ſink it ſo deep in the Soul, that 'tis not in the power of time to work it out, or make it be forgotten. And 'tis theſe Immodeſt Sprinklings, theſe Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Suggeſtions, which makes theſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments, that would otherwiſe be in ſome ſort juſtifiable, to be many times prejudicial to Vertuous Inclinations, to be the Corruption of Youth, and to caſt ſuch ill Seed in the Minds of the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, that the Fruit it brings forth, I fear is not ſo very Chriſtian as it ſhould be, or as ſome pretend, who ſay, they go
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:55678:42"/> to thoſe Diverſions to be inſtructed in <hi>Goodneſs</hi> and <hi>Vertue:</hi> For certainly their <hi>Eyes</hi> and <hi>Ears</hi> muſt be very great <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts,</hi> ſo entirely to ſeparate the Good from the Evil, as to let none of the Droſs and Filth go down with what is pure and Spirit, and prevent all the good Effects of it in the Soul. But however they may be skill'd in this, I cannot but think, if they ſincerely deſire their own Good, they might learn much more of this at home, with a Good Book in a Corner, at a cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er rate, and with more ſecurity. But what, muſt no Diverſion then of a Play be allow'd to Younger People, and others that have leiſure? they muſt expect ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny clamouring Adverſaries, that anſwer this in the Negative. But this Caution then I give, that they be careful to chooſe ſuch as are Innocent, and go but ſeldom: For, believe me, thoſe that go to all Plays indifferently, and grow fond of this Entertainment, muſt needs run a great hazard of defiling all that is good within them, and betray in themſelves a very <hi>Corrupt and Idle Inclination,</hi> who can find no better Employment than living in a Play-houſe. And I can think but little better of thoſe who delight in no other
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:55678:42"/> Books, but in reading <hi>Plays</hi> and <hi>Romances;</hi> for beſides this particular Miſchief, we here ſpeak of, they are apt to make vain, airy and giddy Brains, put people upon extravagancies, keep Youth from ever ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and prepares them for Dreaming, as long as they live.</p>
            <p>Hitherto as to the <hi>Eyes;</hi> but after this, there is ſtill a great care to be us'd in the Government of the <hi>Tongue,</hi> in order to preſerve the Soul Pure and Undefil'd; ſo that whoever deſires to make one of that Bleſſed Number of the <hi>Clean of heart,</hi> muſt, with <hi>David,</hi> ſet a Guard over his Lips, and by no means ſuffer any <hi>Indecent</hi> or <hi>Immodeſt</hi> Word to come out of his Mouth. This is the Command of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who enjoyns all thoſe, that think of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt, <hi>To let no Corrupt Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation proceed out of their Mouths,</hi> and that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs be not once nam'd amongſt them, Epheſ.</hi> 4. 29. 8. 3. This he repeats again <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3. 8. Where his Command is, <hi>Put off Anger, Wrath, Malice, Blaſphemy, Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Communication out of your Mouth.</hi> Is it not plain then, that if this be one of the Conditions requir'd for the laying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide Inſidelity and becoming a Chriſtian, that whoever permits in himſelf, the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:55678:43"/> of <hi>Corrupt Communication,</hi> of <hi>Immodeſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,</hi> or even <hi>Naming what is Filthy,</hi> is ſo much of an infidel ſtill, ſo far an Enemy to Chriſt, inſtead of being a Chriſtian?</p>
            <p>And is it not moſt ſurprizing then, to ſee how frequent this is amongſt thoſe, that profeſs this Name; moſt abominable to hear them, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſpect to God's Command or regard to their Souls, talking like Heathens, like Beaſts, nay like Evil Spirits; for what elſe is this, but the Language of Hell, the Communication of Devils? And who art thou, Chriſtian, that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeſt to ſerve thy God, and art bound by his Law, to ſpeak nothing but to Edification, and art ſo often, amongſt thy Companions, beginning and helping on theſe <hi>filthy Diſcourſes,</hi> as if thy buſineſs were, not to ſerve and honour, but to injure and provoke thy God? For tell me, if thou wert a Fiend, what couldſt thou do more? Thou art by this, a Contemner of thy Maker, an Enemy to thy own Soul, a Promoter of Wickedneſs and a Tempter of the Brethren: And what beyond this, canſt thou have more of a Devil, but his Puniſhment? And canſt thou want this long, who art thus treaſuring up to thy ſelf Anger in the day of wrath? Deceive nor therefore thy ſelf with the Name of <hi>Religion,</hi> be not flatter'd with thy <hi>Praying</hi> or <hi>good Deſigns;</hi> but either <hi>effectually</hi> take care to amend this evil, or believe not thy ſelf to be a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>And is he any better, who, tho he will not talk ſmuttily, yet is ever ready with a <hi>filthy Song,</hi> to make ſport amongſt his Friends? His Religion may be Good, but he's certainly no
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:55678:43"/> better<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> than a <hi>Judas,</hi> who thus betrays the Cauſe of his Maſter, who raiſes up the Devil in as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hearts as there are Hearers, and turns a Friendly and Chriſtian Entertainment into a <hi>Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick</hi> Meeting or Feaſt of <hi>Priapus.</hi> And however this ſort of men may pleaſe themſelves, in the many Smiles they raiſe and the Diverſion they give the Company; yet if they would but once ſeriouſly conſider the part they act, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of that Judgment, which will one day put a long Period to all their Merriment, the Scene, I think, would ſoon be chang'd, and they be willing to make choiſe of an Innocent Sobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, rather than go on in the deluſion of this Brutiſh Mirth and debauch'd Madneſs. For are not they the moſt miſerable of all Sinners; their Crime being ſuch, as to render all the means of Reconciliation and Repentance in ſome manner to them impoſſible? For ſuppoſe they endeavour to amend and repent of this their <hi>Perſonal Fault,</hi> and now begin to hope all is well; what will their condition be, when at the hour of Death ſhall be laid before them, all the Sins they have caus'd, whether by <hi>Immodeſt Diſcourſe</hi> or <hi>Songs,</hi> in others; when they ſhall ſee many Souls, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in the Torments of Hell, that have been condemn'd to thoſe Pains, for Crimes which they have occaſion'd in them? O God, what Confuſion and Deſpair will begin to Seize at that time, when they ſhall find their Repentance ſo far ſhort of their Sins? How will they then think themſelves unfit for Heaven, by whom ſo many burn Hell? Deliver, O Lord, all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians from this deteſtable Vice, and teach thoſe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:55678:44"/> that are guilty of it, not to truſt to an imperfect Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, there is a Reſtraint to be had on the other Senſes: On the <hi>Hearing,</hi> ſo as not to bear with any ſort of <hi>Immodeſt Talk</hi> or <hi>Songs;</hi> but either openly to divert or ſilence it, or, at the leaſt, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from ſuch wicked Company: On the <hi>Hands,</hi> ſo as not to allow them the leaſt Liberty of any thing that has but the <hi>Shew of Evil,</hi> or can poſſibly be ſuſpected of <hi>Indecency.</hi> And here, not to think of what is in private, is there not want of a great Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation as to the Publick; this ſort of <hi>Impudence</hi> being grown ſo Common, that 'tis not ſafe for <hi>Modeſty</hi> and <hi>Vertue</hi> to appear abroad without a Guard, to defend them from the Inſolencies and Abuſes of thoſe Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, who walk the Streets in the Spirits of the Devil, going about like him and ſeeking whom they may devour?</p>
            <p>Thus if all the <hi>Senſes</hi> were kept in order, and the <hi>Phancy</hi> or <hi>Imagination</hi> not permitted to entertain any thing of Evil, there might be ſome hopes of triumphing over this Vice of Impurity, which at preſent, to the ſhame of Chriſtendom, has got ſuch Poſſeſſion, that it abounds both in <hi>Slaves</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi> too; dragging ſome through infinite hardſhips, for its Support and Maintenance; and drawing others into ſuch <hi>Filthy Diſeaſes</hi> and <hi>Torments,</hi> as, it may be, exceed the Invention of the greateſt Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants; and where can theſe Torments end but in others Eternal? Thus dear pay ſome for Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Oh, that men would ſeriouſly think, and not loſe their Souls, for the ſatisfaction of living like Beaſts!</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:55678:44"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
